While the RAG system we built can handle simple
requirements, it comes with some limitations.
What if the query's text is not that similar to
the correct answer?
What if the query is partof a longer conversation
and lacks necessarycontext from earlier?
What if the answer dependson multiple different sub Q&As?
In this lesson, we'll cover some more advanced RAG applications.
This is a fast-moving field of AI engineering
and there are many techniques around but we'lldo just a light survey.
If you want extra practice,implement some of these advanced techniques in thestreamlet app we made in the last lesson.
The firstand simplest way to enhance RAG performance is aset
of techniques called retrieval decoupling.
Decoupling refers to the separation of theretrieved chunk in the vector database via theuser's query
from the retrieved information thatis inserted into the prompt.
In the context ofwhat we recently learned, we are separating thechunks that are similarity searched from thechunks that are injected into the prompt.
For instance, a chunk is retrieved during the retrievalphase.
This particular chunk is expected to containthe information relevant to the query
but thesurrounding chunks are also retrieved and includedin the prompt.
This methodology helps enhancecontextual understanding, reduce ambiguity,
and output richer content generation.
The next techniqueis known as hypothetical document
embeddings orHyDE.
HyDE leverages generative models to create
hypothetical documents based on a given query,
which can then be used to enhance the retrievalprocess by improving the relevance and qualityof the retrieved information.
It can generally bemore useful than RAG by itself and is worth trying.
First, an LLM is used to create a hypotheticaldocument or passage that would answer a userquery or contain relevant information
withoutthe need to reference your vector data.
The hypothetical document is then converted intoembeddings, which capture the semantic meaningof the hypothetical document.
The embeddings ofthe hypothetical document are used to perform asimilarity search against a database of documentembeddings.
This search retrieves actual documentsthat are semantically
similar to the hypotheticaldocument.
The retrieved documents, which areexpected to be highly relevant due to theimproved retrieval process,
are then used bythe generative model to produce the final response.
Sometimes the query sent to your rag system willlack
information about its context.
For instance, it might be an item in a long chatbot historywhere the query only makes sense in referenceto earlier parts of the discussion.
In thesecases, it's useful to rewrite the query for the
user to include more of the necessary context.
This is where contextual query rewriting comesinto play.
This process takes the initial userquery input and retrieves relevant user-relatedcontext from its conversation history
to rewritethe original query to be more specific, clear,
and contextually rich.
The rewriting can involveadding missing information, clarifying ambiguities,or rephrasing for better retrieval effectiveness.
The rewritten query is then used for documentretrieval.
Since the query is now more precise andcontextually appropriate, the retrieved documentsare likely to be more relevant and useful.
Finally,the contextualized query is then sent to theRAG system.
Fusion Search breaks the user queryinto numerous subqueries and each subquery isindependently processed and answered.
It thentakes all the sub-answers and fuses them together
into a single answer.
By combining the outputsof multiple independent retrievals, Fusion Searchaims to provide a more robust set of documents fordownstream processing.
This pattern of dividingtasks into smaller tasks and then recombiningthem is good preparation for agentic design,
whereconcepts like this are done on a bigger scale.
It's a great option if your queries require unpackingelaborate information.
Coming up, you'll applysome of these advanced RAG techniques, such asHyDE and Fusion Search into a series of exercises.